{"text": "I have heard that on one occasion the Blessed One was staying near Rājagaha at the Bamboo Grove, the Squirrels' Sanctuary. And on that occasion, when Ven. Upasena Vaṅgantaputta was alone in seclusion, this line of thinking appeared to his awareness: \"What a gain, what a true gain it is for me that my teacher is the Blessed One, worthy and fully self-awakened; that I have gone forth from home to the homeless life in a well-taught Dhamma & Vinaya; that my companions in the holy life are virtuous and endowed with admirable qualities; that I have achieved culmination in terms of the precepts; that my mind is unified and well-concentrated; that I am an arahant, with effluents ended; that I have great power & great might. Fortunate has been my life; fortunate will be my death.\"", "spans": [{"start": 38, "end": 49, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 83, "end": 95, "label": "LOC"}, {"start": 317, "end": 328, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Now on that occasion Sakka, the deva-king, wanted to give alms to Ven. Mahā Kassapa. So, assuming the appearance of a weaver, he was working a loom, while Sujātā, an asura-maiden, filled the shuttle. Then, as Ven. Mahā Kassapa was going on an almsround that bypassed no donors [1] in Rājagaha, he arrived at Sakka's home. Sakka saw him coming from afar and, on seeing him, came out of house to meet him. Taking the bowl from his hand, entered the house, took cooked rice from the pot, filled the bowl, and gave it back to Ven. Mahā Kassapa. And that gift of alms included many kinds of curry, many kinds of sauces.", "spans": [{"start": 155, "end": 161, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Then Visakha the lay follower, delighting & rejoicing in what Dhammadinna the nun had said, bowed down to her and, keeping her to his right, went to the Blessed One. On arrival, having bowed down to the Blessed One, he sat to one side. As he was sitting there he told the Blessed One the full extent of the conversation he had had with Dhammadinna the nun. When this was said, the Blessed One said to him, \"Dhammadinna the nun is wise, Visakha, a woman of great discernment. If you had asked me those things, I would have answered you in the same way she did. That is the meaning of those things. That is how you should remember it.\"", "spans": [{"start": 5, "end": 12, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 153, "end": 164, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 203, "end": 214, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 272, "end": 283, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 381, "end": 392, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 436, "end": 443, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Saying, \"Yes, lady,\" Visakha the lay follower delighted & rejoiced in what Dhammadinna the nun had said. Then he asked her a further question: \"'The origination of self-identification, the origination of self-identification,' it is said, lady. Which origination of self-identification is described by the Blessed One?\"", "spans": [{"start": 21, "end": 28, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 305, "end": 316, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Then Ven. Upasena said, \"Quick, friends, lift this body of mine onto a couch and carry it outside before it is scattered like a fistful of chaff! Friend Sariputta, in anyone who had the thought, 'I am the eye' or 'The eye is mine,' 'I am the ear' or 'The ear is mine,' 'I am the nose' or 'The nose is mine,' 'I am the tongue' or 'The tongue is mine,' 'I am the body or 'The body is mine,' 'I am the intellect' or 'The intellect is mine': in him there would be an alteration in his body or a change in his faculties. But as for me, the thought does not occur to me that 'I am the eye' or 'The eye is mine,'... 'I am the tongue' or 'The tongue is mine,'... 'I am the intellect' or 'The intellect is mine.' So what alteration should there be in my body, what change should there be in my faculties?\"", "spans": [{"start": 153, "end": 162, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "I have heard that on one occasion the Blessed One was staying near Rājagaha at the Bamboo Grove, the Squirrels' Sanctuary. And on that occasion, when Ven. Upasena Vaṅgantaputta was alone in seclusion, this line of thinking appeared to his awareness: \"What a gain, what a true gain it is for me that my teacher is the Blessed One, worthy and fully self-awakened; that I have gone forth from home to the homeless life in a well-taught Dhamma & Vinaya; that my companions in the holy life are virtuous and endowed with admirable qualities; that I have achieved culmination in terms of the precepts; that my mind is unified and well-concentrated; that I am an arahant, with effluents ended; that I have great power & great might. Fortunate has been my life; fortunate will be my death.\"", "spans": [{"start": 38, "end": 49, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 83, "end": 95, "label": "LOC"}, {"start": 317, "end": 328, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Then the Blessed One, comprehending with his awareness the line of thinking that had appeared to Ven. Upasena Vaṅgantaputta's awareness, on that occasion exclaimed:", "spans": [{"start": 9, "end": 20, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "When this was said, Ven. Sariputta said to Ven. Upasena, \"But we don't see any alteration in your body or change in your faculties.\"", "spans": [{"start": 25, "end": 34, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "And on that occasion Ven. Subhūti was sitting not far from the Blessed One, his legs crossed, his body held erect, having attained a concentration free from directed thought.", "spans": [{"start": 63, "end": 74, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "And on that occasion Ven. Sāriputta, Ven. Mahā Moggalāna, Ven. Mahā Kassapa, Ven. Mahā Kaccāyana, Ven. Mahā Koṭṭhita, Ven. Mahā Kappina, Ven. Mahā Cunda, Ven. Anuruddha, Ven. Revata, and Ven. Nanda [1] went to the Blessed One. The Blessed One saw them coming from afar and, on seeing them, addressed the monks, \"Monks, those are brahmans who are coming. Monks, those are brahmans who are coming.\"", "spans": [{"start": 147, "end": 152, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 214, "end": 225, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 231, "end": 242, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 329, "end": 337, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 371, "end": 379, "label": "NORP"}]}
{"text": "Now at that time Ven. Upavana was standing in front of the Blessed One, fanning him.", "spans": [{"start": 59, "end": 70, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Then Mara the Evil One — sad & dejected at realizing, \"Kisa Gotami the nun knows me\" — vanished right there.", "spans": [{"start": 5, "end": 9, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Then King Pasenadi Kosala went to the bhikkhuni Khema and, on arrival, having bowed down to her, sat to one side. As he was sitting there he said to her, \"Now then, lady, does the Tathagata exist after death?\"", "spans": [{"start": 180, "end": 189, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Setting at Savatthi. Then, in the morning, the bhikkhuni Uppalavanna dressed... she stood at the foot of a sala tree in full flower.", "spans": [{"start": 11, "end": 19, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "Saying, \"Yes, lady,\" Visakha the lay follower delighted & rejoiced in what Dhammadinna the nun had said.", "spans": [{"start": 21, "end": 28, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Then Mara the Evil One, desiring to arouse fear, trepidation, and terror in the bhikkhuni Kisagotami, desiring to make her fall away from concentration, approached her and addressed her in verse.", "spans": [{"start": 5, "end": 9, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "When this was said, Ven. Ananda said to the Blessed One, \"Lord, may the Blessed One not be totally unbound in this little town, this dusty town, this branch township. There are other great cities: Campa , Rajagaha , Savatthi , Saketa , Kosambi , Vanarasi . May the Blessed One be totally unbound there. In those cities there are many wealthy noble warriors, brahmans, & householders who have high confidence in the Tathagata. They will conduct the Tathagata's funeral.\"", "spans": [{"start": 25, "end": 31, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 44, "end": 55, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 72, "end": 83, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 205, "end": 213, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 216, "end": 224, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 236, "end": 243, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 265, "end": 276, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 358, "end": 366, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 415, "end": 424, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 448, "end": 457, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Then the thought occurred to Ven. Channa, \"This Ven. Ananda is staying at Kosambi in Ghosita's Park. He has been praised by the Teacher and is esteemed by his knowledgeable fellows in the holy life. He is capable of teaching me the Dhamma so that I might see the Dhamma, and I have sudden trust in him. Why don't I go to Ven. Ananda?\"", "spans": [{"start": 53, "end": 59, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 74, "end": 81, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 326, "end": 332, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "On one occasion Ven. Musila , Ven. Pavittha , Ven. Narada , and Ven. Ananda were staying in Kosambi at Ghosita's monastery .", "spans": [{"start": 69, "end": 75, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 92, "end": 99, "label": "GPE"}]}
