{"text": "Once the Blessed One was dwelling at Savatthi, in Anathapindika's park. At that time the Venerable Sariputta was at Nalaka village in the Magadha country, and was sick, suffering, gravely ill. The Novice Cunda was his attendant.\n", "spans": [{"start": 9, "end": 20, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 37, "end": 45, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 50, "end": 70, "label": "LOC"}, {"start": 89, "end": 108, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 116, "end": 122, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 138, "end": 145, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 204, "end": 209, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "That being the case, venerable Gotama dwells in greater pleasure than King Seniya Bimbisara of Magadha.", "spans": [{"start": 21, "end": 37, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 70, "end": 91, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 95, "end": 102, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "That being the case, venerable Gotama dwells in greater pleasure than King Seniya Bimbisara of Magadha.", "spans": [{"start": 21, "end": 37, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 70, "end": 91, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 95, "end": 102, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "Sunīdha & Vassakāra, the chief ministers of Magadha, lord, are building a city at Pāṭali Village to preempt the Vajjians.", "spans": [{"start": 0, "end": 7, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 10, "end": 19, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 44, "end": 51, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 82, "end": 96, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 112, "end": 120, "label": "NORP"}]}
{"text": "Then King Ajatasattu Vedehiputta of Magadha built a burial mound and held a ceremony for the Blessed One's relics in Rajagaha.\n", "spans": [{"start": 5, "end": 32, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 36, "end": 43, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 93, "end": 104, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 117, "end": 125, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "\"Sunidha and Vassakara, Lord, the chief ministers of Magadha, are building a fortress at Pataligama, in defence against the Vajjis.\n", "spans": [{"start": 1, "end": 8, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 13, "end": 22, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 53, "end": 60, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 89, "end": 99, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 124, "end": 130, "label": "NORP"}]}
{"text": "\"\"Do as now seems fit to you, brahman.\" And the brahman Vassakara, the chief minister of Magadha, approving of the Blessed One's words and delighted by them, rose from his seat and departed.\n", "spans": [{"start": 48, "end": 65, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 89, "end": 96, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "Surely the venerable Niganthas said that rashly and without reflecting... for instead, I should be asked, Who lives in greater pleasure: King Seniya Bimbisara of Magadha or venerable Gotama?\n", "spans": [{"start": 11, "end": 30, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 137, "end": 158, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 162, "end": 169, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "Ānanda, it's as if they had consulted the devas of the Thirty-three: That's how Sunīdha & Vassakāra, the chief ministers of Magadha, are building a city at Pāṭali Village to preempt the Vajjians.\n", "spans": [{"start": 0, "end": 6, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 42, "end": 67, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 80, "end": 87, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 90, "end": 99, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 124, "end": 131, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 156, "end": 170, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 186, "end": 194, "label": "NORP"}]}
{"text": " Yes, friend Gotama, we said that rashly and without reflecting... but let that be. We now ask you, venerable Gotama: Who lives in greater pleasure: King Seniya Bimbisara of Magadha or venerable Gotama?\n", "spans": [{"start": 13, "end": 19, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 100, "end": 116, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 149, "end": 170, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 174, "end": 181, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 195, "end": 201, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "At one time the Buddha was living in Magadha, just below the hills, near a brahman village called Ekanala. At that time the brahman Kasibharadvaja had yoked together a number of plows, for it was planting time.\n\n", "spans": [{"start": 16, "end": 22, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 37, "end": 44, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 98, "end": 105, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 124, "end": 146, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "In that case, Niganthas, I will question you in return. Answer as you like. What do you think: Can King Seniya Bimbisara of Magadha — without moving his body, without uttering a word — dwell sensitive to unalloyed pleasure for seven days & nights?\n", "spans": [{"start": 14, "end": 23, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 99, "end": 120, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 124, "end": 131, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "But, friend Gotama, it's not the case that pleasure is to be attained through pleasure. Pleasure is to be attained through pain. For if pleasure were to be attained through pleasure, then King Seniya Bimbisara of Magadha would attain pleasure, for he lives in greater pleasure than you, friend Gotama.\n", "spans": [{"start": 5, "end": 18, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 188, "end": 209, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 287, "end": 300, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Then Sunīdha & Vassakāra, the chief ministers of Magadha, understanding the Blessed One's acquiescence, went to their rest-house. On arrival, after having exquisite staple & non-staple food prepared in their rest-house, they announced the time to the Blessed One: \"It's time, Master Gotama. The meal is ready.\"\n\n", "spans": [{"start": 5, "end": 12, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 15, "end": 24, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 49, "end": 56, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 76, "end": 87, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 251, "end": 262, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 276, "end": 289, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Then King Ajatasattu Vedehiputta of Magadha heard, \"The Blessed One, they say, has been totally unbound in Kusinara.\" So he sent an envoy to the Kusinara Mallans: \"The Blessed One was a noble warrior. I, too, am a noble warrior. I deserve a share of the Blessed One's bone-relics. I, too, will build a burial mound and hold a ceremony for them.\"\n", "spans": [{"start": 6, "end": 32, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 36, "end": 43, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 56, "end": 67, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 107, "end": 115, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 145, "end": 161, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 168, "end": 179, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Very well then, Aggivessana, I will cross-question you on this matter. Answer as you see fit. What do you think? Would a consecrated, noble-warrior king — such as King Pasenadi of Kosala or King Ajātasattu Vedehiputta of Magadha — wield the power in his own domain to execute those who deserve execution, to fine those who deserve to be fined, and to banish those who deserve to be banished?\n", "spans": [{"start": 16, "end": 27, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 163, "end": 176, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 180, "end": 186, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 190, "end": 217, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 221, "end": 228, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": " Just as though, Visakha, one might have power, dominion and kingship over sixteen great countries abounding in the seven treasures — that is to say, Anga, Magadha, Kasi, Kosala, Vajji, Malla, Ceti, Vansa, Kure, Pancala, Maccha, Surasena, Assaka, Avanti, Gandhara and Kamboja, yet it is not worth a sixteenth part of the Uposatha undertaken with its eight practices. For what reason? Miserable is kingship over men compared with heavenly bliss.", "spans": [{"start": 17, "end": 24, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 150, "end": 154, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 156, "end": 163, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 165, "end": 169, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 171, "end": 177, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 179, "end": 184, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 186, "end": 191, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 193, "end": 197, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 199, "end": 204, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 206, "end": 210, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 212, "end": 219, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 221, "end": 227, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 229, "end": 237, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 239, "end": 245, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 247, "end": 253, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 255, "end": 263, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 268, "end": 275, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": " Then King Pasenadi Kosala, with a cavalry of roughly 500 horsemen, drove out of Savatthi and entered the monastery. Driving as far as the ground was passable for chariots, he got down from his chariot and went on foot to the Blessed One. On arrival, having bowed down, he sat to one side. As he was sitting there, the Blessed One said to him, \"What is it, great king? Has King Seniya Bimbisara of Magadha provoked you, or have the Licchavis of Vesali or some other hostile king?\n", "spans": [{"start": 6, "end": 26, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 81, "end": 89, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 226, "end": 237, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 319, "end": 330, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 373, "end": 395, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 398, "end": 405, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 432, "end": 441, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 445, "end": 451, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "Thereupon the brahman Vassakara spoke thus to the Blessed One: \"If the Vajjis, Venerable Gotama, were endowed with only one or another of these conditions leading to welfare, their growth would have to be expected, not their decline. What then of all the seven? No harm, indeed, can be done to the Vajjis in battle by Magadha's king, Ajatasattu, except through treachery or discord. Well, then, Venerable Gotama, we will take our leave, for we have much to perform, much work to do.\"\n", "spans": [{"start": 22, "end": 31, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 50, "end": 61, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 71, "end": 77, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 79, "end": 95, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 298, "end": 304, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 318, "end": 325, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 328, "end": 332, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 334, "end": 344, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 395, "end": 411, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "At that time Sunidha and Vassakara, the chief ministers of Magadha, were building a fortress at Pataligama in defense against the Vajjis\n", "spans": [{"start": 13, "end": 20, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 25, "end": 34, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 59, "end": 66, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 96, "end": 106, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 130, "end": 136, "label": "NORP"}]}
{"text": "No, lord. King Seniya Bimbisara of Magadha hasn't provoked me, nor have the Licchavis of Vesali, nor has some other hostile king. There is a bandit in my realm, lord, named Angulimala: brutal, bloody-handed, devoted to killing & slaying, showing no mercy to living beings. He has turned villages into non-villages, towns into non-towns, settled countryside into unsettled countryside. Having repeatedly killed human beings, he wears a garland made of fingers. I am going to stamp him out.\n", "spans": [{"start": 10, "end": 31, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 35, "end": 42, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 76, "end": 85, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 89, "end": 95, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 173, "end": 183, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "On one occasion the Blessed One was living at Dakkhinagiri (monastery), in the brahmana village Ekanala, in Magadha. Now at that time, it being the sowing season, five hundred plows of the brahman Kasibharadvaja were put to use. Then in the forenoon the Blessed One having dressed himself, took bowl and (double) robe, and went to the place where brahman Kasibharadvaja's work was going on. It was the time of food distribution by the brahman, and the Blessed One drew near, and stood at one side. Bharadvaja seeing the Blessed One standing there for alms said to him:\n\n", "spans": [{"start": 20, "end": 31, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 46, "end": 58, "label": "LOC"}, {"start": 96, "end": 103, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 108, "end": 115, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 197, "end": 211, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 254, "end": 265, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 355, "end": 369, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 452, "end": 463, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 498, "end": 508, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 520, "end": 531, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "Yes, Master Gotama, he would wield the power in his own domain to execute those who deserve execution, to fine those who deserve to be fined, and to banish those who deserve to be banished. Even these oligarchic groups, such as the Vajjians & Mallans, wield the power in their own domains to execute those who deserve execution, to fine those who deserve to be fined, and to banish those who deserve to be banished, [5] to say nothing of a consecrated, noble-warrior king such as King Pasenadi of Kosala, or King Ajātasattu Vedehiputta of Magadha. He would wield it, and he would deserve to wield it.\n", "spans": [{"start": 5, "end": 18, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 232, "end": 240, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 243, "end": 250, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 480, "end": 493, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 497, "end": 503, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 508, "end": 535, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 539, "end": 546, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "Sunīdha & Vassakāra, with their own hands, served & satisfied the community of monks, with the Buddha at its head, with exquisite staple & non-staple food. Then, when the Blessed One had finished his meal and withdrawn his hand from the bowl, Sunīdha & Vassakāra, taking a low seat, sat to one side. As they were sitting there, the Blessed One gave his approval with these verses:\n", "spans": [{"start": 0, "end": 7, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 10, "end": 19, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 95, "end": 101, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 171, "end": 182, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 243, "end": 250, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 253, "end": 262, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 332, "end": 343, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "I have heard that on one occasion the Blessed One was staying at Rajagaha , in Jivaka Komarabhacca 's mango grove, with a large community of monks — 1,250 monks in all. Now at that time — it being the observance day, the full-moon night of the water-lily season, the fourth month of the rains — King Ajatasattu of Magadha, the son of Queen Videha , was sitting on the roof terrace of his palace surrounded by his ministers. Then he felt inspired to exclaim: \"How wonderful is this moonlit night! How beautiful... How lovely... How inspiring... How auspicious is this moonlit night! What brahman or contemplative should we visit tonight who might enlighten and bring peace to our mind?\"\n\n", "spans": [{"start": 38, "end": 49, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 65, "end": 73, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 79, "end": 98, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 102, "end": 113, "label": "LOC"}, {"start": 295, "end": 310, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 314, "end": 321, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 334, "end": 346, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "And the king of Magadha, Ajatasattu, son of the Videhi queen, erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Rajagaha, and in their honor held a festival.\n", "spans": [{"start": 16, "end": 23, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 25, "end": 35, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 48, "end": 60, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 101, "end": 112, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 116, "end": 124, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "The Licchavis of Vesali erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Vesali, and in their honor held a festival. \n\n", "spans": [{"start": 4, "end": 13, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 17, "end": 23, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 63, "end": 74, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 78, "end": 84, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "The Sakyas of Kapilavatthu erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Kapilavatthu, and in their honor held a festival. \n ", "spans": [{"start": 4, "end": 10, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 14, "end": 26, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 66, "end": 77, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 81, "end": 93, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "The Bulis of Allakappa erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Allakappa, and in their honor held a festival.  \n ", "spans": [{"start": 4, "end": 9, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 13, "end": 22, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 62, "end": 73, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 77, "end": 86, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "The Kolis of Ramagama erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Ramagama, and in their honor held a festival. \n ", "spans": [{"start": 4, "end": 9, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 13, "end": 21, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 61, "end": 72, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 76, "end": 84, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "The Vethadipa brahman erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Vethadipa, and in their honor held a festival. \n ", "spans": [{"start": 4, "end": 13, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 14, "end": 21, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 61, "end": 72, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 76, "end": 85, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "The Mallas of Pava erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Pava, and in their honor held a festival.\n", "spans": [{"start": 4, "end": 10, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 14, "end": 18, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 58, "end": 69, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 73, "end": 77, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "The Mallas of Kusinara erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Kusinara, and in their honor held a festival. \n", "spans": [{"start": 4, "end": 10, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 14, "end": 22, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 62, "end": 73, "label": "PERSON"}, {"start": 77, "end": 85, "label": "GPE"}]}
{"text": "The brahman Dona erected a stupa over the urn, and in its honor held a festival. \n", "spans": [{"start": 4, "end": 11, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 12, "end": 16, "label": "PERSON"}]}
{"text": "And the Moriyas of Pipphalivana erected a stupa over the ashes at Pipphalivana, and in their honor held a festival. \n", "spans": [{"start": 8, "end": 15, "label": "NORP"}, {"start": 19, "end": 31, "label": "GPE"}, {"start": 66, "end": 78, "label": "GPE"}]}

