{"text": "\"Just as though, Visakha, one might have power, dominion and kingship [11] over sixteen great countries abounding in the seven treasures [12] — that is to say, Anga, Magadha, Kasi, Kosala, Vajji, Malla, Ceti, Vansa, Kure, Pancala, Maccha, Surasena, Assaka, Avanti, Gandhara and Kamboja, yet it is not worth a sixteenth part of the Uposatha undertaken with its eight practices. For what reason? Miserable is kingship over men compared with heavenly bliss.", 
"entities": [
	["PERSON", "Visakha"], 
	["GPE", "Anga"], 
	["GPE", "Magadha"], 
	["GPE", "Kasi"], 
	["GPE", "Kosala"], 
	["GPE", "Vajji"], 
	["GPE", "Malla"], ["GPE", "Vansa"], ["GPE", "Kure"], 
	["GPE", "Pancala"], ["GPE", "Surasena"], ["GPE", "Assaka"], ["GPE", "Avanti"], ["GPE", "Gandhara"], ["GPE", "Kamboja"], ["EVENT", "Uposatha"]]}


{"text": "\"Suppose that one were to exercise kingship, rule, & sovereignty over these sixteen great lands replete with the seven treasures, i.e., over the Angas , Maghadans , Kasis , Kosalans , Vajjians , Mallas , Cetis , Vansans , Kurus , Pañcalas , Macchas , Surasenas , Assakas , Avantis , Gandharans , & Kambojans : It would not be worth one-sixteenth of this Uposatha endowed with eight factors. Why is that? Kingship over human beings is a meager thing when compared with heavenly bliss.", "entities": [
	["NORP", "Angas"], ["NORP", "Maghadans"], ["NORP", "Kasis"], ["NORP", "Kosalans"], ["NORP", "Vajjians"], ["NORP", "Mallas"], ["NORP", "Cetis"], ["NORP", "Vansans"], ["NORP", "Kurus"], ["NORP", "Pañcalas"], ["NORP", "Macchas"], ["NORP", "Surasenas"], ["NORP", "Assakas"], ["NORP", "Avantis"], ["NORP", "Gandharans"], ["NORP", "Kambojans"], ["EVENT", "Uposatha"]]}


{"text": "On one occasion the Blessed One was staying near Kusinara in Upavattana , the Sal Tree Grove of the Mallans , on the occasion of his total Unbinding. Then the Blessed One addressed the monks, \"I exhort you, monks: All fabrications are subject to decay. Bring about completion by being heedful.\" Those were the Tathagata's last words.", "entities": [["PERSON", "Blessed One"], ["GPE", "Kusinara"], ["GPE", "Upavattana"], ["LOC", "Sal Tree Grove"], ["NORP", "Mallans"], ["PERSON", "Blessed One"], ["PERSON", "Tathagata"]]}
