{"text": ". On one occasion, the Buddha [1] was living near the town of Rajagaha [2] at a spot in the Bamboo Grove called the Squirrel's Feeding Place.", "entities": [[83, 89, "LOC"], [90, 95, "LOC"]], "meta": {"term": "Bamboo Grove", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.31.0.ksw0.html", "title": "Sigalovada Sutta", "para_seq": 2, "hits": 2, "first_offset": 83}}
{"text": ". Then the Blessed One addressed the venerable Ananda: \"See, Ananda, how this misguided man Udayin interferes. I knew, Ananda, that this misguided man Udayin would unreasonably interfere now. To begin with it was the three kinds of feeling that were asked about by the wanderer Potaliputta. If, when this misguided man Samiddhi was asked, he had answered the wanderer Potaliputta thus: 'After doing an intentional kamma by way of body, speech and mind (whose result is) to be felt as pleasure, he feels pleasure; after doing an intentional kamma by way of body, speech and mind (whose result is) to be felt as pain, he feels pain; after doing an intentional kamma by way of body, speech and mind (whose result is) to be felt as neither-pain-nor-pleasure, he feels neither-pain-nor-pleasure' — by answering him thus, Ananda, the misguided man Samiddhi would have given the wanderer Potaliputta the right answer. Besides, Ananda, who are the foolish thoughtless wanderers of other sects that they will understand the Tathagata's Great Exposition of Kamma? (But) if you, Ananda, would listen to the Tathagata expounding the Great Exposition of Kamma (you might understand it). [3]", "entities": [[45, 51, "PERSON"], [59, 65, "PERSON"], [117, 123, "PERSON"], [814, 820, "PERSON"], [918, 924, "PERSON"], [1066, 1072, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ananda", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.136.nymo.html", "title": "Maha Kammavibhanga Sutta", "para_seq": 17, "hits": 6, "first_offset": 45}}
{"text": ". Then, when it was morning, the Venerable Sariputta dressed, and taking his bowl and outer robe, went into Vesali for alms. Then he heard Sunakkhatta, son of the Licchavis, making this statement before the Vesali assembly. When he had wandered for alms in Vesali and had returned from his almsround, after his meal he went to the Blessed One, and after paying homage to him, he sat down at one side and told the Blessed One what Sunakkhatta was saying.", "entities": [[106, 112, "GPE"], [205, 211, "GPE"], [255, 261, "GPE"]], "meta": {"term": "Vesali", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.012.ntbb.html", "title": "Maha-sihanada Sutta", "para_seq": 3, "hits": 3, "first_offset": 106}}
{"text": ". Thus spoke the Venerable Ananda, but the Blessed One answered him, saying: \"What more does the community of bhikkhus expect from me, Ananda? I have set forth the Dhamma without making any distinction of esoteric and exoteric doctrine; there is nothing, Ananda, with regard to the teachings that the Tathagata holds to the last with the closed fist of a teacher who keeps some things back. Whosoever may think that it is he who should lead the community of bhikkhus, or that the community depends upon him, it is such a one that would have to give last instructions respecting them. But, Ananda, the Tathagata has no such idea as that it is he who should lead the community of bhikkhus, or that the community depends upon him. So what instructions should he have to give respecting the community of bhikkhus?", "entities": [[25, 31, "PERSON"], [133, 139, "PERSON"], [253, 259, "PERSON"], [587, 593, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ananda", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.1-6.vaji.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 150, "hits": 4, "first_offset": 25}}
{"text": "(e) \"Having a single formless perception internally, one sees forms externally as blue, blue in their color, blue in their features, blue in their glow. Just as a flax-flower is blue, blue in its color, blue in its features, blue in its glow, or just as Benares muslin, smooth on both sides, is blue, blue in its color, blue in its features, blue in its glow; in the same way, having a single formless perception internally, one sees forms externally as blue, blue in their color, blue in their features, blue in their glow. Mastering them, one has the perception, 'I know; I see.' This is the fifth dimension of [mental] mastery.", "entities": [[254, 261, "GPE"]]}
{"text": "[ Ananda :] \"There is the case, my friend, where a monk, withdrawn from sensuality, withdrawn from unskillful qualities, enters & remains in the first jhana: rapture & pleasure born from withdrawal, accompanied by directed thought & evaluation. He remains touching with his body in whatever way there is an opening there [see AN 9.35 ]. It is to this extent that one is described by the Blessed One as a bodily witness, though with a sequel.", "entities": [[2, 8, "PERSON"], [387, 398, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "[ At Veluvana the wanderer Acela-Kassapa ( Naked Kassapa ) questioned the Buddha :]", "entities": [[0, 8, "LOC"]], "meta": {"term": "Veluvana", "nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn12.017x.wlsh.html", "title": "Acela Sutta", "para_seq": 1, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 0}}
{"text": "[The concluding verse added by the 'Theras of the First Council:]", "entities": []}
{"text": "[When this was said, the Blessed One responded:] \" I tell you , friend, that it is not possible by traveling to know or see or reach a far end of the cosmos where one does not take birth, age, die, pass away, or reappear. But at the same time, I tell you that there is no making an end of suffering & stress without reaching the end of the cosmos. Yet it is just within this fathom-long body, with its perception & intellect, that I declare that there is the cosmos, the origination of the cosmos, the cessation of the cosmos, and the path of practice leading to the cessation of the cosmos.\"", "entities": [[25, 36, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "*[ Sallekha (= sam-lekha) is derived from the verbal root likh, to scratch; hence likhati (a) to scratch in, to write; (b) to scratch off, to remove: samlikhati, \"to remove fully.\" An interesting parallel is \"ascesis,\" derived from the Greek askeuein, to scratch. The rendering by \"effacement\" is Ñanamoli Thera's; Soma Thera has \"cancelling\"; I. B. Horner, \"expunging.\"]", "entities": []}
{"text": "\" [ 3 ] And what are the fermentations to be abandoned by using? There is the case where a monk, reflecting appropriately, uses the robe simply to counteract cold, to counteract heat, to counteract the touch of flies, mosquitoes, wind, sun, & reptiles; simply for the purpose of covering the parts of the body that cause shame.", "entities": []}
{"text": "\" [ 5 ] And what are the fermentations to be abandoned by avoiding? There is the case where a monk, reflecting appropriately, avoids a wild elephant, a wild horse, a wild bull, a wild dog, a snake, a stump, a bramble patch, a chasm, a cliff, a cesspool, an open sewer. Reflecting appropriately, he avoids sitting in the sorts of unsuitable seats, wandering to the sorts of unsuitable habitats, and associating with the sorts of bad friends that would make his knowledgeable friends in the holy life suspect him of evil conduct. The fermentations, vexation, or fever that would arise if he were not to avoid these things do not arise for him when he avoids them. These are called the fermentations to be abandoned by avoiding.", "entities": []}
{"text": "\" [ 6 ] And what are the fermentations to be abandoned by destroying? There is the case where a monk, reflecting appropriately, does not tolerate an arisen thought of sensuality. He abandons it, dispels it, & wipes it out of existence.", "entities": []}
{"text": "\" Even so , my friend Sariputta, are those who have people like you as their fellows in the holy life, teaching them, admonishing them out of sympathy, desiring their welfare. For now that I have heard this explanation of the Dhamma from you, my mind — through lack of clinging/sustenance — has been released from the effluents.\"", "entities": [[22, 31, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\" There are these four marvelous & amazing qualities in Ananda. If a group of monks approaches to see Ananda, they are gratified at the sight of him. If he speaks Dhamma to them, they are gratified with what he says. Before they are sated, he falls silent. If a group of nuns approaches to see Ananda... If a group of male lay followers approaches to see Ananda... If a group of female lay followers approaches to see Ananda, they are gratified at the sight of him. If he speaks Dhamma to them, they are gratified with what he says. Before they are sated, he falls silent. These are the four marvelous & amazing qualities in Ananda. There are these four marvelous & amazing qualities in a wheel-turning monarch. If a group of noble warriors approaches to see him... If a group of brahmans approaches to see him... If a group of householders approaches to see him... If a group of contemplatives approaches to see him, they are gratified at the sight of him. If he speaks to them, they are gratified with what he says. Before they are sated, he falls silent. In the same way, monks, there are these four marvelous & amazing qualities in Ananda. If a group of monks... a group of nuns... a group of male lay followers... a group of female lay followers approaches to see Ananda, they are gratified at the sight of him. If he speaks Dhamma to them, they are gratified with what he says. Before they are sated, he falls silent. These are the four marvelous & amazing qualities in Ananda.\"", "entities": [[54, 60, "PERSON"], [100, 106, "PERSON"], [292, 298, "PERSON"], [353, 359, "PERSON"], [416, 422, "PERSON"], [623, 629, "PERSON"], [1134, 1140, "PERSON"], [1267, 1273, "PERSON"], [1474, 1480, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ananda", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.5-6.than.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 41, "hits": 9, "first_offset": 54}}
{"text": "\"And for what reason is a disciple of a Tathagata worthy of a burial mound? [At the thought,] 'This is the burial mound of a disciple of a Tathagata,' many people will brighten their minds. Having brightened their minds there, then — on the break-up of the body, after death — they will reappear in a good destination, the heavenly world...", "entities": [[40, 49, "PERSON"], [139, 148, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"And what are the ideas fit for attention that he does attend to? Whatever ideas such that, when he attends to them, the unarisen fermentation of sensuality does not arise in him, and the arisen fermentation of sensuality is abandoned; the unarisen fermentation of becoming does not arise in him, and the arisen fermentation of becoming is abandoned; the unarisen fermentation of ignorance does not arise in him, and the arisen fermentation of ignorance is abandoned. These are the ideas fit for attention that he does attend to. Through his not attending to ideas unfit for attention and through his attending to ideas fit for attention, unarisen fermentations do not arise in him, and arisen fermentations are abandoned.", "entities": []}
{"text": "\"And what are the ideas fit for attention that he does not attend to? Whatever ideas such that, when he attends to them, the unarisen fermentation of sensuality does not arise in him, and the arisen fermentation of sensuality is abandoned; the unarisen fermentation of becoming does not arise in him, and arisen fermentation of becoming is abandoned; the unarisen fermentation of ignorance does not arise in him, and the arisen fermentation of ignorance is abandoned. These are the ideas fit for attention that he does not attend to. Through his attending to ideas unfit for attention and through his not attending to ideas fit for attention, both unarisen fermentations arise in him, and arisen fermentations increase.", "entities": []}
{"text": "\"And what are the ideas unfit for attention that he does not attend to? Whatever ideas such that, when he attends to them, the unarisen fermentation of sensuality arises in him, and the arisen fermentation of sensuality increases; the unarisen fermentation of becoming arises in him, and arisen fermentation of becoming increases; the unarisen fermentation of ignorance arises in him, and the arisen fermentation of ignorance increases. These are the ideas unfit for attention that he does not attend to.", "entities": []}
{"text": "\"As you say, friend, Ven. Samiddhi responded to Ven. Ānanda.", "entities": [[40, 46, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ānanda", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.136.than.html", "title": "Maha Kammavibhanga Sutta", "para_seq": 9, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 40}}
{"text": "\"As you say, lord,\" Ven. Ānanda responded to the Blessed One.", "entities": [[12, 18, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ānanda", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.136.than.html", "title": "Maha Kammavibhanga Sutta", "para_seq": 16, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 12}}
{"text": "\"But, monk, in what way has the Blessed One said that sensual pleasures are subject to time, of much stress, much despair, & greater drawbacks? And how is this Dhamma visible here-&-now, not subject to time, inviting all to come & see, pertinent, to be known by the wise for themselves?\"", "entities": [[32, 43, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"Cunda, as to those several views that arise in the world concerning self-doctrines and world-doctrines, if [the object] in which [4] these views arise, in which they underlie and become active, [5] is seen with right wisdom [6] as it actually is, [7] thus: 'This is not mine, [8] this I am not, [9] this is not my self' [10] — then the abandoning of these views, their discarding, [11] takes place in him [who thus sees].", "entities": [[1, 6, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"Friend, concerning these five clinging-aggregates described by the Blessed One — i.e., form as a clinging-aggregate... feeling... perception... fabrications... consciousness as a clinging-aggregate: With regard to these five clinging-aggregates, there is nothing I assume to be self or belonging to self.\"", "entities": [[68, 79, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"Furthermore, in the case of the highest type of men (uttamapurisa) who have noble aspirations, who act considerately and wisely, also their mental concentration and their wisdom, just as their morality, is conducive to the weal and happiness of others. In that way, too, compassion is the root of all virtues, and therefore it has been mentioned at the beginning.", "entities": []}
{"text": "\"Harmlessness (i.e., the principle of non-violence) has the characteristic mark of making one refrain from immorality which, on its part, has the mark of harming. Hence harmlessness is an especially strong productive cause of morality; and morality, again, is the basis for concentration of mind, while concentration is the basis for wisdom. In that way harmlessness (non-violence) is the root of all virtues.", "entities": []}
{"text": "\"How is it, Master Gotama, when Master Gotama is asked if the monk reappears... does not reappear... both does & does not reappear... neither does nor does not reappear, he says, '...doesn't apply' in each case. At this point, Master Gotama, I am befuddled; at this point, confused. The modicum of clarity coming to me from your earlier conversation is now obscured.\"", "entities": [[19, 25, "PERSON"], [39, 45, "PERSON"], [234, 240, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"It is in this respect, Moggallana, that a monk, in brief, is released through the ending of craving, utterly complete, utterly free from bonds, a follower of the utterly holy life, utterly consummate: foremost among human & heavenly beings.\"", "entities": [[24, 34, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"It is not possible, Cunda, that one who is himself not restrained, not disciplined and not quenched [as to his passions], [24] should make others restrained and disciplined, should make them attain to the full quenching [of passions]. [25] But it is possible, Cunda, that one who is himself restrained, disciplined and fully quenched [as to his passions] should make others restrained and disciplined, should make them attain to the full quenching [of passions]. Even so, Cunda: [26]", "entities": [[21, 26, "PERSON"], [261, 266, "PERSON"], [473, 478, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"It's amazing, friend Sariputta. It's astounding, friend Sariputta, how well that was said by Ven. Sariputta. And I rejoice in Ven. Sariputta's good statements with regard to these 36 topics. [1] If a monk teaches the Dhamma for the sake of disenchantment, dispassion, & cessation with regard to aging & death, he deserves to be called a monk who is a speaker of Dhamma. If he practices for the sake of disenchantment, dispassion, & cessation with regard to aging & death, he deserves to be called a monk who practices the Dhamma in accordance with the Dhamma. [2] If — through disenchantment, dispassion, cessation, and lack of clinging/sustenance with regard to aging & death — he is released, then he deserves to be called a monk who has attained Unbinding in the here-&-now.", "entities": [[16, 25, "PERSON"], [51, 60, "PERSON"], [93, 102, "PERSON"], [126, 135, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Sariputta", "nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn12.067.than.html", "title": "Nalakalapiyo Sutta", "para_seq": 12, "hits": 4, "first_offset": 16}}
{"text": "\"It's amazing, my friend. It's astounding, my friend, how well-said that was by friend Ananda. And we will remember friend Ananda as endowed with these six qualities: Friend Ananda has mastered the Dhamma: dialogues, narratives of mixed prose and verse, explanations, verses, spontaneous exclamations, quotations, birth stories, amazing events, question & answer sessions. Friend Ananda teaches the Dhamma in detail — as he has heard it, as he has remembered it — to others. Friend Ananda gets others to recite the Dhamma in detail — as they have heard it, as they have remembered it. Friend Ananda holds a group chanting of the Dhamma in detail — as he has heard it, as he has remembered it. Friend Ananda thinks about & evaluates the Dhamma as he has heard it, as he has remembered it; he contemplates it with his intellect. Friend Ananda enters the Rains in monasteries in which there are senior monks who are learned, who know the tradition, who are holders of the Dhamma, the Vinaya, & the Matika. Having approached them periodically, he questions them & quizzes them: 'How it this, venerable sirs? What is the meaning of this?' They make open for friend Ananda what wasn't open, make plain what wasn't plain, dispel doubt on various doubtful points.\"", "entities": [[81, 87, "PERSON"], [117, 123, "PERSON"], [168, 174, "PERSON"], [374, 380, "PERSON"], [476, 482, "PERSON"], [586, 592, "PERSON"], [694, 700, "PERSON"], [828, 834, "PERSON"], [1154, 1160, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ananda", "nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an06.051.than.html", "title": "Ananda Sutta", "para_seq": 7, "hits": 9, "first_offset": 81}}
{"text": "\"Monks, associate with Sariputta & Moggallana. Consort with Sariputta & Moggallana. They are wise monks, sympathetic toward their fellows in the holy life. Like the mother giving birth: That's Sariputta. Like the nurse raising a child after it's born: That's Moggallana. Sariputta trains [others] to the fruit of stream-entry; Moggallana, to the highest goal. [1] Sariputta is capable of declaring, teaching, describing, setting forth, revealing, explaining, and making plain the four noble truths in detail.\"", "entities": [[22, 31, "PERSON"], [59, 68, "PERSON"], [192, 201, "PERSON"], [270, 279, "PERSON"], [363, 372, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Sariputta", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.141.than.html", "title": "Saccavibhanga Sutta", "para_seq": 4, "hits": 5, "first_offset": 22}}
{"text": "\"Monks, follow Sariputta and Moggallana; associate with Sariputta and Moggallana. Wise monks do help (materially and spiritually) those who live the holy life. Monks, Sariputta is like unto a mother, Moggallana is like unto a foster-mother to a child. Sariputta, monks, trains (beings) in the path [2] of stream-attainment. Moggallana in the highest goal (arahantship). [3] Sariputta, monks, is able to proclaim, teach, lay down, establish, open up, analyze, and elucidate the Four Noble Truths.\"", "entities": [[14, 23, "PERSON"], [55, 64, "PERSON"], [166, 175, "PERSON"], [251, 260, "PERSON"], [373, 382, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Sariputta", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.141.piya.html", "title": "Saccavibhanga Sutta", "para_seq": 5, "hits": 5, "first_offset": 14}}
{"text": "\"Not a valid question,\" the Blessed One said. \"I don't say 'clings.' If I were to say 'clings,' then 'Who clings?' would be a valid question. But I don't say that. When I don't say that, the valid question is 'From what as a requisite condition comes clinging?' And the valid answer is, 'From craving as a requisite condition comes clinging. From clinging as a requisite condition comes becoming. From becoming as a requisite condition comes birth. From birth as a requisite condition, then aging & death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, distress, & despair come into play. Such is the origination of this entire mass of stress & suffering. [1]", "entities": [[28, 39, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"Now, (after harmlessness), the salutary courses of action (kusala-kammapatha; 2-11) are to show that these states are produced by harmlessness. Then follow the eight states of rightness (11-18) to show that they must be brought about by basing them on morality, which is the root of these virtues. Now the separation from the hindrances (21-23, and 16, 17) is included to indicate that this is the primary task for one intent on purifying (his practice of) the eightfold path. Then follows the cleansing from the defilements (24-33) to indicate that effacement is accomplished by giving up anger (24), etc. And the cleansing from the defilements will be successful when aided by amenability to advice, noble friendship and heedful diligence (34-36).", "entities": []}
{"text": "\"Now, Ananda, I have taught the practice conducive to the imperturbable. I have taught the practice conducive to the dimension of nothingness. I have taught the practice conducive to the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. I have taught the way to cross over the flood by going from one support to the next, the noble liberation. Whatever a teacher should do — seeking the welfare of his disciples, out of sympathy for them — that have I done for you. Over there are the roots of trees; over there, empty dwellings. Practice jhana, Ananda. Don't be heedless. Don't later fall into regret. This is our message to you all.\"", "entities": [[6, 12, "PERSON"], [548, 554, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"Now, Ānanda, in the case where the contemplative or brahman says, 'So there really are evil actions, there really is the result of misconduct,' I allow him that. When he says, 'For I saw the case where a person who took life... & held wrong view, with the breakup of the body, after death, has reappeared in a plane of deprivation, a bad destination, a lower realm, hell,' I allow him that, too. But when he says, 'Anyone who takes life... & hold wrong view: They all, on the breakup of the body, after death, reappear in a plane of deprivation, a bad destination, a lower realm, hell,' I don't allow him that. And when he says, 'Whoever knows this, knows rightly; whoever knows otherwise, their knowledge is wrong,' I don't allow him that. When, insisting through obstinacy & grasping right there on what was seen by himself, known by himself, understood by himself, he states: 'Only this is true. Everything otherwise is worthless,' I don't allow him that, either. Why is that? Because the Tathāgata's knowledge with regard to the greater analysis of action is otherwise.", "entities": [[0, 6, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ānanda", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.136.than.html", "title": "Maha Kammavibhanga Sutta", "para_seq": 29, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 0}}
{"text": "\"Now, what, friend Sāriputta, is the pleasant in this Teaching and Discipline, and what is the painful?\"", "entities": [[13, 22, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Sāriputta", "nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an10.066.niza.html", "title": "Dutiya Sukha Sutta", "para_seq": 2, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 13}}
{"text": "\"Now, what, friend Sāriputta, is the pleasant, and what is the painful?\"", "entities": [[13, 22, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Sāriputta", "nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an10.065.niza.html", "title": "Pathama Sukha Sutta", "para_seq": 2, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 13}}
{"text": "\"Obvious is also the harm done to others by deception, by causing dissension and by backbiting. The mark of harming others is also attached to gossip because it takes away what is beneficial and causes to arise what is not beneficial; to covetousness, as it causes one to take what is not given; to ill will, as it causes killing, etc.; to wrong views, as they are the cause of all that is un-beneficial. One who holds wrong views may, in the conviction of acting righteously, kill living beings and incite others to do likewise. There is nothing to say about other (and lesser immoral acts induced by false views).", "entities": []}
{"text": "\"Once in this same Savatthi there was a woman whose mother died. Owing to her mother's death she went mad, out of her mind, and wandering from street to street, crossroads to crossroads, would say, 'Have you seen my mother? Have you seen my mother?' It's through this sequence of events that it may be understood how sorrow, lamentation, pain, distress, & despair are born from one who is dear, come springing from one who is dear.", "entities": [[19, 27, "GPE"]]}
{"text": "\"Reflecting appropriately, he uses lodging simply to counteract cold, to counteract heat, to counteract the touch of flies, mosquitoes, wind, sun, & reptiles; simply for protection from the inclemencies of weather and for the enjoyment of seclusion.", "entities": []}
{"text": "\"Suppose a man — in need of heartwood, seeking heartwood, wandering in search of heartwood — were to enter a forest taking a sharp ax. There he would see a large plantain trunk: straight, young, immature. He would cut it at the root and, having cut it at the root, cut off the crown. Having cut off the crown, he would unfurl the leaf sheaths. Unfurling the leaf sheaths, he wouldn't even find sapwood there, to say nothing of heartwood. In the same way, Aggivessana, when you are interrogated, rebuked, & pressed by me with regard to your own statement, you are empty, void, mistaken. But it was you who made this statement before the assembly in Vesālī: 'I see no contemplative or brahman, the head of an order, the head of a group, or even one who claims to be an arahant, rightly self-awakened, who — engaged in debate with me — would not shiver, quiver, shake, & break out in sweat under the armpits. Even if I were to engage a senseless stump in debate, it — engaged with me in debate — would shiver, quiver, & shake, to say nothing of a human being.' But now some drops of sweat coming out of your forehead, drenching your upper robe, are landing on the ground, whereas now I have no sweat on my body.\" And the Blessed One uncovered his golden-colored body to the assembly. When this was said, Saccaka the Nigaṇṭha-son fell silent, abashed, sitting with his shoulders drooping, his head down, brooding, at a loss for words.", "entities": [[647, 653, "GPE"]], "meta": {"term": "Vesālī", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.035.than.html", "title": "Cula-Saccaka Sutta", "para_seq": 59, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 647}}
{"text": "\"Then not long after the wandering sectarians had left, this thought occurred to me: 'If I am questioned again by those wandering sectarians, how will I answer in such a way that will I speak in line with what the Blessed One has said, will not misrepresent the Blessed One with what is unfactual, will answer in line with the Dhamma, and no one whose thinking is in line with the Dhamma will have grounds for criticizing me?'\"", "entities": [[214, 225, "PERSON"], [262, 273, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"Then there is the case, Ānanda, where a certain contemplative or brahman — through ardency, exertion, commitment, heedfulness, & right attention — touches the sort of concentration of awareness that, when his mind is thus concentrated, he sees with the divine eye, pure and surpassing the human, that person — the case where one who abstains from taking life, abstains from taking what is not given, abstains from illicit sex, abstains from lying, abstains from speaking divisively, abstains from speaking abusively, abstains from idle chatter, is not covetous, not malevolent, & holds right view, with the breakup of the body, after death, reappears in a good destination, a heavenly world.", "entities": [[24, 30, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ānanda", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.136.than.html", "title": "Maha Kammavibhanga Sutta", "para_seq": 25, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 24}}
{"text": "\"Then there is the case, Ānanda, where a certain contemplative or brahman — through ardency, exertion, commitment, heedfulness, & right attention — touches the sort of concentration of awareness that, when his mind is thus concentrated, he sees with the divine eye, pure and surpassing the human, that person — the case where one who abstains from taking life, abstains from taking what is not given, abstains from illicit sex, abstains from lying, abstains from speaking divisively, abstains from speaking abusively, abstains from idle chatter, is not covetous, not malevolent, & holds right view, with the breakup of the body, after death, reappears in a plane of deprivation, a bad destination, a lower realm, hell.", "entities": [[24, 30, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ānanda", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.136.than.html", "title": "Maha Kammavibhanga Sutta", "para_seq": 27, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 24}}
{"text": "\"Then there is the case, Ānanda, where a certain contemplative or brahman — through ardency, exertion, commitment, heedfulness, & right attention — touches the sort of concentration of awareness that, when his mind is thus concentrated, he sees with the divine eye, pure and surpassing the human, that person — the case where one who takes life, takes what is not given (steals), engages in illicit sex, lies, speaks divisively, speaks abusively, engages in idle chatter, is covetous, malevolent, & holds wrong view, with the breakup of the body, after death, has reappeared in a good destination, a heavenly world.", "entities": [[24, 30, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ānanda", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.136.than.html", "title": "Maha Kammavibhanga Sutta", "para_seq": 23, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 24}}
{"text": "\"There is the case, Ānanda, where a certain contemplative or brahman — through ardency, exertion, commitment, heedfulness, & right attention — touches the sort of concentration of awareness that, when his mind is thus concentrated, he sees with the divine eye, pure and surpassing the human, that person — the case where one who takes life, takes what is not given (steals), engages in illicit sex, lies, speaks divisively, speaks abusively, engages in idle chatter, is covetous, malevolent, & holds wrong view, with the breakup of the body, after death, has reappeared in a plane of deprivation, a bad destination, a lower realm, hell.", "entities": [[19, 25, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ānanda", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.136.than.html", "title": "Maha Kammavibhanga Sutta", "para_seq": 21, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 19}}
{"text": "\"This is how he attends inappropriately : 'Was I in the past? Was I not in the past? What was I in the past? How was I in the past? Having been what, what was I in the past? Shall I be in the future? Shall I not be in the future? What shall I be in the future? How shall I be in the future? Having been what, what shall I be in the future?' Or else he is inwardly perplexed about the immediate present: 'Am I? Am I not? What am I? How am I? Where has this being come from? Where is it bound?'", "entities": []}
{"text": "\"What do you think, Aggivessana? When one adheres to stress, holds to stress, is attached to stress, and envisions of stress that 'This is mine; this is my self; this is what I am,' would he comprehend stress or dwell having totally destroyed stress?\"", "entities": [[20, 31, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"What do you think, Aggivessana? When you say, 'Feeling is my self... Perception is my self... Fabrications are my self... Consciousness is my self,' do you wield power over that consciousness: 'May my consciousness be thus, may my consciousness not be thus'?\"", "entities": [[20, 31, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"What do you think, Tissa: In one who is not without passion, desire, love, thirst, fever, & craving for feeling... perception... fabrications, does there arise sorrow, lamentation, pain, distress, & despair from change & alteration in his fabrications?\"", "entities": [[20, 25, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "\"You've gone too far, friend Visakha. You can't keep holding on up to the limit of questions. For the holy life gains a footing in Unbinding, culminates in Unbinding, has Unbinding as its final end. If you wish, go to the Blessed One and ask him the meaning of these things. Whatever he says, that's how you should remember it.\"", "entities": [[29, 36, "PERSON"], [222, 233, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "1. Then the Blessed One, getting ready in the forenoon, took bowl and robe and went into Vesali for alms. After the alms round and meal, on his return, he looked upon Vesali with the elephant's look, [36] and said to the Venerable Ananda: \"This, Ananda, is the last time that the Tathagata will look upon Vesali. Come, Ananda, let us go to Bhandagama .\"", "entities": [[86, 92, "GPE"], [164, 170, "GPE"], [302, 308, "GPE"]], "meta": {"term": "Vesali", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.1-6.vaji.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 230, "hits": 3, "first_offset": 86}}
{"text": "12. \"But herein, Cunda, effacement should be practiced by you: [16]", "entities": [[17, 22, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "15. \"Cunda, as all unsalutary states lead downward and all salutary states lead upward, even so, Cunda:", "entities": [[5, 10, "PERSON"], [97, 102, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "16 . Then Ambapali the courtesan came to know: \"The Blessed One, they say, has arrived at Vesali and is now staying in my Mango Grove.\" And she ordered a large number of magnificent carriages to be made ready, mounted one of them herself, and accompanied by the rest, drove out from Vesali towards her park. She went by carriage as far as the carriage could go, then alighted; and approaching the Blessed One on foot, she respectfully greeted him and sat down at one side. And the Blessed One instructed Ambapali the courtesan in the Dhamma and roused, edified, and gladdened her.", "entities": [[85, 91, "GPE"], [278, 284, "GPE"]], "meta": {"term": "Vesali", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.1-6.vaji.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 125, "hits": 2, "first_offset": 85}}
{"text": "17. \"Thus, Cunda, I have shown to you the instruction on effacement, I have shown to you the instruction on thought's arising, I have shown to you the instruction on avoidance, I have shown to you the instruction on the way upward, I have shown to you the instruction on quenching.", "entities": [[11, 16, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "18. \"What can be done for his disciples by a Master who seeks their welfare and has compassion and pity on them, that I have done for you, Cunda. [27] There are these roots of trees, there are empty places. Meditate, Cunda, do not delay, lest you later regret it. 'This is my message to you.\"", "entities": [[139, 144, "PERSON"], [217, 222, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "18. Then the Licchavi of Vesali came to know: \"The Blessed One, they say, has arrived at Vesali and is now staying in Ambapali's grove.\" And they ordered a large number of magnificent carriages to be made ready, each mounted one, and accompanied by the rest, drove out from Vesali. Now, of these Licchavis, some were in blue, with clothing and ornaments all of blue, while others were in yellow, red, and white.", "entities": [[21, 27, "GPE"], [85, 91, "GPE"], [270, 276, "GPE"]], "meta": {"term": "Vesali", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.1-6.vaji.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 128, "hits": 3, "first_offset": 21}}
{"text": "2. Then one evening the venerable Maha-Cunda [1] rose from meditative seclusion and went to the Blessed One. Having paid homage to him, he sat down at one side and spoke thus to the Blessed One:", "entities": [[39, 44, "PERSON"], [96, 107, "PERSON"], [182, 193, "PERSON"]]}
{"text": "28. \"It is, Ananda, as if Sunidha and Vassakara had taken counsel with the gods of the Thirty-three. For I beheld, Ananda, with the heavenly eye, pure and transcending the faculty of men, a large number of deities, counted in thousands, that have taken possession of sites at Pataligama. In the region where deities of great power prevail, officials of great power are bent on constructing edifices; and where deities of medium and lesser power prevail, officials of medium and lesser power are bent on constructing edifices. Truly, Ananda, as far as the Aryan race extends and trade routes spread, this will be the foremost city Pataliputta , a trade-center. [16] But Pataliputta, Ananda, will be assailed by three perils — fire, water, and dissension.\"", "entities": [[0, 6, "PERSON"], [103, 109, "PERSON"], [521, 527, "PERSON"], [670, 676, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ananda", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.1-6.vaji.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 87, "hits": 4, "first_offset": 0}}
{"text": "42. And the king of Magadha, Ajatasattu, son of the Videhi queen, erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Rajagaha, and in their honor held a festival. The Licchavis of Vesali erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Vesali, and in their honor held a festival. The Sakyas of Kapilavatthu erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Kapilavatthu, and in their honor held a festival. The Bulis of Allakappa erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Allakappa, and in their honor held a festival. The Kolis of Ramagama erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Ramagama, and in their honor held a festival. The Vethadipa brahman erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Vethadipa, and in their honor held a festival. The Mallas of Pava erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Pava, and in their honor held a festival. The Mallas of Kusinara erected a stupa over the relics of the Blessed One at Kusinara, and in their honor held a festival. The brahman Dona erected a stupa over the urn, and in its honor held a festival. And the Moriyas of Pipphalivana erected a stupa over the ashes at Pipphalivana, and in their honor held a festival.", "entities": [[171, 177, "GPE"], [232, 238, "GPE"]], "meta": {"term": "Vesali", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.1-6.vaji.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 450, "hits": 2, "first_offset": 171}}
{"text": "49. \"It is so, Ananda. There are two occasions, Ananda, when the skin of the Tathagata appears exceedingly clear and radiant. Which are these two? The night, Ananda, when the Tathagata becomes fully enlightened in unsurpassed, supreme Enlightenment, and the night when the Tathagata comes to his final passing away into the state of Nibbana in which no element of clinging remains. These, Ananda, are the two occasions on which the skin of the Tathagata appears exceedingly clear and radiant.", "entities": [[0, 6, "PERSON"], [33, 39, "PERSON"], [143, 149, "PERSON"], [374, 380, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ananda", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.1-6.vaji.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 288, "hits": 4, "first_offset": 0}}
{"text": "56. \"So also at the Banyan Grove, at Robbers' Cliff, at the Sattapanni Cave on the Vebhara Mountain, at the Black Rock of Isigili , at the Serpents' Pool in the Cool Forest, at the Tapoda Grove, at the Bamboo Grove in the Squirrels' Feeding-ground, at Jivaka's Mango Grove, and at Small Nook in the Deer Park I spoke to you in the same words, saying: 'Pleasant, Ananda, is Rajagaha, pleasant are these places. Whosoever, Ananda, has developed... Therefore the Tathagata could, if he so desired, remain throughout a world-period or until the end of it.'", "entities": [[19, 24, "LOC"], [180, 185, "LOC"], [194, 200, "LOC"], [201, 206, "LOC"], [259, 264, "LOC"]], "meta": {"term": "Bamboo Grove", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.1-6.vaji.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 218, "hits": 5, "first_offset": 19}}
{"text": "56. \"So also at the Banyan Grove, at Robbers' Cliff, at the Sattapanni Cave on the Vebhara Mountain, at the Black Rock of Isigili , at the Serpents' Pool in the Cool Forest, at the Tapoda Grove, at the Bamboo Grove in the Squirrels' Feeding-ground, at Jivaka's Mango Grove, and at Small Nook in the Deer Park I spoke to you in the same words, saying: 'Pleasant, Ananda, is Rajagaha, pleasant are these places. Whosoever, Ananda, has developed... Therefore the Tathagata could, if he so desired, remain throughout a world-period or until the end of it.'", "entities": [[19, 24, "LOC"], [180, 185, "LOC"], [201, 206, "LOC"], [244, 250, "LOC"], [251, 252, "LOC"], [253, 264, "LOC"]], "meta": {"term": "Jivaka's Mango Grove", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.1-6.vaji.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 218, "hits": 7, "first_offset": 19}}
{"text": "56. Then the Blessed One spoke to the Venerable Ananda, saying: \"It may come to pass, Ananda, that someone will cause remorse to Cunda the metalworker, saying: 'It is no gain to you, friend Cunda, but a loss, that it was from you the Tathagata took his last alms meal, and then came to his end.' Then, Ananda, the remorse of Cunda should be dispelled after this manner: 'It is a gain to you, friend Cunda, a blessing that the Tathagata took his last alms meal from you, and then came to his end. For, friend, face to face with the Blessed One I have heard and learned: \"There are two offerings of food which are of equal fruition, of equal outcome, exceeding in grandeur the fruition and result of any other offerings of food. Which two? The one partaken of by the Tathagata before becoming fully enlightened in unsurpassed, supreme Enlightenment; and the one partaken of by the Tathagata before passing into the state of Nibbana in which no element of clinging remains. By his deed the worthy Cunda has accumulated merit which makes for long life, beauty, well being, glory, heavenly rebirth, and sovereignty.\"' Thus, Ananda, the remorse of Cunda the metalworker should be dispelled.\"", "entities": [[44, 50, "PERSON"], [82, 88, "PERSON"], [298, 304, "PERSON"], [1115, 1121, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ananda", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.1-6.vaji.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 294, "hits": 4, "first_offset": 44}}
{"text": "57. \"So also at Vesali, Ananda, at different times the Tathagata has spoken to you, saying: 'Pleasant, Ananda, is Vesali; pleasant are the shrines of Udena, Gotamaka, Sattambaka, Bahuputta, Sarandada, and Capala. Whosoever, Ananda, has developed... Therefore the Tathagata could, if he so desired, remain throughout a world-period or until the end of it.'", "entities": [[8, 14, "GPE"], [106, 112, "GPE"]], "meta": {"term": "Vesali", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.1-6.vaji.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 220, "hits": 2, "first_offset": 8}}
{"text": "9-10. And the Venerable Ananda told his thought to the Blessed One. The Blessed One said: \"Throughout the tenfold world-system, Ananda, there are hardly any of the deities that have not gathered together to look upon the Tathagata. For a distance of twelve yojanas around the Sala Grove of the Mallas in the vicinity of Kusinara there is not a spot that could be pricked with the tip of a hair that is not filled with powerful deities. And these deities, Ananda, are complaining: 'From afar have we come to look upon the Tathagata. For rare in the world is the arising of Tathagatas, Arahants, Fully Enlightened Ones. And this day, in the last watch of the night, the Tathagata's Parinibbana will come about. But this bhikkhu of great powers has placed himself right in front of the Blessed One, concealing him, so that now, at the very end, we are prevented from looking upon him.' Thus, Ananda, the deities complain.\"", "entities": [[10, 16, "PERSON"], [114, 120, "PERSON"], [441, 447, "PERSON"], [875, 881, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ananda", "nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.16.1-6.vaji.html", "title": "Maha-parinibbana Sutta", "para_seq": 307, "hits": 4, "first_offset": 10}}
{"text": "At one time the Blessed One was residing in Jetavana, the monastery of Anathapindika, near Savatthi. At that time the Blessed One, having called all the bhikkhus together, addressed them thus: \"Bhikkhus!\" The bhikkhus answered in assent: \"Lord!\" (The bhikkhus then prepared themselves for the following teaching.) The Blessed One then gave the following teaching on Uposatha.", "entities": [[37, 45, "LOC"]], "meta": {"term": "Jetavana", "nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an08.041.vaka.html", "title": "Uposatha Sutta", "para_seq": 2, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 37}}
{"text": "At Savatthi. \"Monks, any desire-passion with regard to contact at the eye is a defilement of the mind. Any desire-passion with regard to contact at the ear... contact at the nose... contact at the tongue... contact at the body... contact at the intellect is a defilement of the mind. When, with regard to these six bases, the defilements of awareness are abandoned, then the mind is inclined to renunciation. The mind fostered by renunciation feels malleable for the direct knowing of those qualities worth realizing.\"", "entities": [[3, 11, "GPE"]]}
{"text": "At Savatthi. \"Monks, any desire-passion with regard to intentions involving forms is a defilement of the mind. Any desire-passion with regard to intentions involving sounds... intentions involving aromas... intentions involving flavors... intentions involving tactile sensations... intentions involving ideas is a defilement of the mind. When, with regard to these six bases, the defilements of awareness are abandoned, then the mind is inclined to renunciation. The mind fostered by renunciation feels malleable for the direct knowing of those qualities worth realizing.\"", "entities": [[3, 11, "GPE"]]}
{"text": "At Savatthi. \"Monks, perception of forms is inconstant, changeable, alterable. Perception of sounds... Perception of smells... Perception of tastes... Perception of tactile sensations... Perception of ideas is inconstant, changeable, alterable.", "entities": [[3, 11, "GPE"]]}
{"text": "At Sāvatthī... There the Blessed One said this:", "entities": [[0, 8, "GPE"]], "meta": {"term": "Sāvatthī", "nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn22.022.niza.html", "title": "Bhāra Sutta", "para_seq": 1, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 0}}
{"text": "Become active (samudacaranti). Comy.: \"Wrong views have arrived at the (action-) doors of body and speech,\" i.e., which have found expression in words and deeds.", "entities": []}
{"text": "Comy.: \"The overrater's meditative absorption is neither 'effacement' nor is it the 'path of practice for effacement' (sallekha-patipada). And why not? Because that jhana is not used by him as a basis for insight; that is, after rising from jhana he does not scrutinize the (physical and mental) formations\" (see Visuddhimagga transl. by Ñanamoli, Ch. XVIII, 3). His jhana produces only one-pointedness of mind, and is, as our text says, an \"abiding in ease here and now.\"", "entities": []}
{"text": "I have heard that on one occasion the Blessed One was staying near Vesālī , at the Gabled Hall in the Great Forest. And on that occasion Saccaka the Nigaṇṭha-son was dwelling in Vesālī — a debater, a sophist, [1] well-regarded by people at large. He made this statement before the assembly in Vesālī: \"I see no contemplative or brahman, the head of an order, the head of a group, or even one who claims to be an arahant, rightly self-awakened, who — engaged in debate with me — would not shiver, quiver, shake, & break out in sweat under the armpits. Even if I were to engage a senseless stump in debate, it — engaged with me in debate — would shiver, quiver, & shake, to say nothing of a human being.\"", "entities": [[65, 71, "GPE"], [176, 182, "GPE"], [291, 297, "GPE"]], "meta": {"term": "Vesālī", "nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.035.than.html", "title": "Cula-Saccaka Sutta", "para_seq": 1, "hits": 3, "first_offset": 65}}
{"text": "I have heard that on one occasion Ven. Ananda was staying in Kosambi , at Ghosita 's Park. Then a certain nun said to a certain man, \"Go, my good man, to my lord Ananda and, on arrival, bowing your head to his feet in my name, tell him, 'The nun named such-and-such, venerable sir, is sick, in pain, severely ill. She bows her head to the feet of her lord Ananda and says, \"It would be good if my lord Ananda were to go to the nuns' quarters, to visit this nun out of sympathy for her.\"'\"", "entities": [[37, 43, "PERSON"], [160, 166, "PERSON"], [354, 360, "PERSON"], [400, 406, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"term": "Ananda", "nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an04.159.than.html", "title": "Bhikkhuni Sutta", "para_seq": 1, "hits": 4, "first_offset": 37}}
{"text": "I have heard that on one occasion Ven. Ananda was staying in Kosambi , at Ghosita 's Park. Then a certain nun said to a certain man, \"Go, my good man, to my lord Ananda and, on arrival, bowing your head to his feet in my name, tell him, 'The nun named such-and-such, venerable sir, is sick, in pain, severely ill. She bows her head to the feet of her lord Ananda and says, \"It would be good if my lord Ananda were to go to the nuns' quarters, to visit this nun out of sympathy for her.\"'\"", "entities": [[59, 66, "GPE"]], "meta": {"term": "Kosambi", "nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an04.159.than.html", "title": "Bhikkhuni Sutta", "para_seq": 1, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 59}}
{"text": "On one occasion a certain monk, a Vajjian princeling, was dwelling near Vesali in a forest thicket. And on that occasion an all-night festival was being held in Vesali. The monk — lamenting as he heard the resounding din of wind music, string music, & gongs coming from Vesali, on that occasion recited this verse:", "entities": [[65, 71, "GPE"], [154, 160, "GPE"], [263, 269, "GPE"]], "meta": {"term": "Vesali", "nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn09.009.than.html", "title": "Vajjiputta Sutta", "para_seq": 1, "hits": 3, "first_offset": 65}}
{"text": "On one occasion the Blessed One was living near Savatthi at Jetavana at Anathapindika's monastery. At that time at Savatthi a certain monk had died bitten by a snake. Thereupon many monks approached the Buddha and having saluted him sat beside him. So seated those monks spoke thus to the Blessed One:", "entities": [[53, 61, "LOC"]], "meta": {"term": "Jetavana", "nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an04.067.piya.html", "title": "Ahi Sutta", "para_seq": 2, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 53}}
{"text": "On one occasion the Blessed One was living near Savatthi at Jetavana at Anathapindika's monastery. At that time Suriya, the sun deity, was seized by Rahu, Lord of Asuras. Thereupon calling to mind the Blessed One, Suriya, the Sun deity, recited this stanza:", "entities": [[53, 61, "LOC"]], "meta": {"term": "Jetavana", "nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn02.010.piya.html", "title": "Suriya Sutta", "para_seq": 2, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 53}}
{"text": "On one occasion the Blessed One was living near Savatthi at Jetavana at Anathapindika's monastery. Then he addressed the monks saying, \"Monks.\" — \"Venerable Sir,\" said the monks, by way of reply. The Blessed One then spoke as follows:", "entities": [[53, 61, "LOC"]], "meta": {"term": "Jetavana", "nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an11.016.piya.html", "title": "Metta (Mettanisamsa) Sutta", "para_seq": 2, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 53}}
{"text": "On one occasion the Blessed One was living near Savatthi at Jetavana at the monastery of Anathapindika. Now at that time, the Venerable Girimananda was afflicted with a disease, was suffering therefrom, and was gravely ill. Thereupon the Venerable Ananda approached the Buddha and having saluted him sat beside him. So seated the Venerable Ananda said this to the Blessed One:", "entities": [[53, 61, "LOC"]], "meta": {"term": "Jetavana", "nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an10.060.piya.html", "title": "Girimananda Sutta", "para_seq": 2, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 53}}
{"text": "On one occasion the Blessed One was living near Savatthi, at Jetavana at Anathpindika's monastery. At that time Candima, the moon deity, was seized by Rahu, lord of Asura. Thereupon calling to mind the Blessed One, Candima, the moon deity, recited this stanza:", "entities": [[54, 62, "LOC"]], "meta": {"term": "Jetavana", "nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn02.009.piya.html", "title": "Candima Sutta", "para_seq": 2, "hits": 1, "first_offset": 54}}
