
{"text": "\"Now, it is because of the person who will alight on the lawfulness, the rightness of skillful mental qualities if he gets to see the Tathagata and gets to hear the Dhamma & Discipline proclaimed by the Tathagata — but not if he doesn't — that the teaching of the Dhamma has been allowed. And it is because there is this sort of person that the other sorts of persons are to be taught the Dhamma as well [on the chance that they may actually turn out to need and benefit from the teaching].", "entities": [[134, 143, "PERSON"], [203, 212, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an03.022.than.html", "title": "Gilana Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"There would, my friend. \"For one who loves becoming, who is fond of becoming, who cherishes becoming, who does not know or see, as it actually is present, the cessation of becoming, there occurs the thought, 'The Tathagata exists after death' or 'The Tathagata does not exist after death' or 'The Tathagata both exists and does not exist after death' or 'The Tathagata neither exists nor does not exist after death.'", "entities": [[214, 223, "PERSON"], [252, 261, "PERSON"], [298, 307, "PERSON"], [360, 369, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn44.006.than.html", "title": "Sariputta-Kotthita Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"Pleasant feeling is pleasant in remaining, & painful in changing, friend Visakha. Painful feeling is painful in remaining & pleasant in changing. Neither-pleasant-nor-painful feeling is pleasant in occurring together with knowledge, and painful in occurring without knowledge.\"", "entities": [[74, 81, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.044.than.html", "title": "Culavedalla Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "Then in the early morning, a large number of monks, having put on their robes and carrying their bowls & outer robes, went into Savatthi for alms. Having gone for alms in Savatthi, after the meal, returning from their alms round, they went to the Blessed One and, on arrival, having bowed down to him, sat to one side. As they were sitting there, they said to the Blessed One: \"Just now, lord, King Ajatasattu of Magadha, the son of Queen Videha, raising a fourfold army, marched toward Kasi against King Pasenadi Kosala. King Pasenadi heard, 'King Ajatasattu of Magadha, the son of Queen Videha, they say, has raised a fourfold army and is marching toward Kasi against me.' So King Pasenadi, raising a fourfold army, launched a counter-attack toward Kasi against King Ajatasattu. Then King Ajatasattu & King Pasenadi fought a battle, and in that battle King Ajatasattu defeated King Pasenadi. King Pasenadi, defeated, marched back to his capital at Savatthi.\"", "entities": [[128, 136, "GPE"], [171, 179, "GPE"], [247, 258, "PERSON"], [364, 375, "PERSON"], [399, 409, "PERSON"], [413, 420, "GPE"], [433, 445, "PERSON"], [487, 491, "GPE"], [500, 520, "PERSON"], [522, 535, "PERSON"], [549, 559, "PERSON"], [563, 570, "GPE"], [583, 595, "PERSON"], [657, 661, "GPE"], [678, 691, "PERSON"], [751, 755, "GPE"], [769, 779, "PERSON"], [791, 801, "PERSON"], [804, 817, "PERSON"], [859, 869, "PERSON"], [879, 892, "PERSON"], [894, 907, "PERSON"], [950, 958, "GPE"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn03.014.than.html", "title": "Sangama Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\" Great king , this was said by the Blessed One who knows & sees, worthy and rightly self-awakened: 'Come now, monks: Keep guarding the doors to your sense faculties. On seeing a form with the eye, do not grasp at any theme or variations by which — if you were to dwell without restraint over the faculty of the eye — evil, unskillful qualities such as greed or distress might assail you. Practice with restraint. Guard the faculty of the eye. Achieve restraint with regard to the faculty of the eye.", "entities": [[36, 47, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn35.127.than.html", "title": "Bharadvaja Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "Then the Blessed One, leaving the road, went to sit at the root of a certain tree — his legs crossed, his body erect, with mindfulness established to the fore. Then Dona, following the Blessed One's footprints, saw him sitting at the root of the tree: confident, inspiring confidence, his senses calmed, his mind calmed, having attained the utmost control & tranquility, tamed, guarded, his senses restrained, a naga. [1] On seeing him, he went to him and said, \"Master, are you a deva?\" [2]", "entities": [[9, 20, "PERSON"], [185, 196, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an04.036.than.html", "title": "Dona Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "[The Blessed One said:] \"Ananda, true was the exposition that Pañcakanga the carpenter would not accept from Ven. Udayin. And true was the exposition that Ven. Udayin would not accept from Pañcakanga the carpenter. There is the exposition by which I have spoken of two feelings, the exposition by which I have spoken of three feelings ... five feelings ... six feelings ... eighteen feelings ... 36 feelings ... 108 feelings. [1] Thus I have taught the Dhamma by means of exposition. When I have taught the Dhamma by means of exposition, it can be expected that when there are those who do not consent to, assent to, or accept what is well-said and well-stated by one another, there will be arguing, quarreling, & disputing, and they will dwell wounding one another with the sword of the tongue. Thus I have taught the Dhamma by means of exposition. When I have taught the Dhamma by means of exposition, it can be expected that when there are those who do consent to, assent to, & accept what is well-said and well-stated by one another, they will live in harmony, with courtesy, without quarreling, like milk mixed with water, regarding one another with friendly eyes.", "entities": [[5, 16, "PERSON"], [25, 31, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.059.than.html", "title": "Bahuvedaniya Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"Ananda, when knowing — as they actually are — the origination, passing away, allure, drawbacks of — and escape from — these seven stations of consciousness and two spheres, a monk is released through lack of clinging, he is said to be a monk released through discernment.", "entities": [[1, 7, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.15.0.than.html", "title": "Maha-nidana Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "When this was said, Ven. Moggallana said to the Blessed One: \"Briefly, lord, in what respect is a monk released through the ending of craving, utterly complete, utterly free from bonds, a follower of the utterly holy life, utterly consummate: foremost among human & heavenly beings?\"", "entities": [[25, 35, "PERSON"], [48, 59, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an07.058.than.html", "title": "Capala (Pacala) Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"This, too, is called a footprint of the Tathagata, a scratch mark of the Tathagata, a tusk slash of the Tathagata, but a disciple of the noble ones would not yet come to the conclusion, 'The Blessed One is rightly self-awakened; the Dhamma is well-taught by the Blessed One; the Sangha of the Blessed One's disciples has practiced rightly.'", "entities": [[41, 50, "PERSON"], [74, 83, "PERSON"], [105, 114, "PERSON"], [192, 203, "PERSON"], [263, 274, "PERSON"], [294, 305, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.027.than.html", "title": "Cula-hatthipadopama Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"Then there is the case, Ānanda, where a certain contemplative or brahman — through ardency, exertion, commitment, heedfulness, & right attention — touches the sort of concentration of awareness that, when his mind is thus concentrated, he sees with the divine eye, pure and surpassing the human, that person — the case where one who abstains from taking life, abstains from taking what is not given, abstains from illicit sex, abstains from lying, abstains from speaking divisively, abstains from speaking abusively, abstains from idle chatter, is not covetous, not malevolent, & holds right view, with the breakup of the body, after death, reappears in a plane of deprivation, a bad destination, a lower realm, hell.", "entities": [[25, 31, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.136.than.html", "title": "Maha Kammavibhanga Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "Replying, \"As you say, friends,\" to the elder monks, Ven. Dasaka went to Ven. Khemaka and on arrival said to him, \"The elders, friend Khemaka, say to you, 'Concerning these five clinging-aggregates described by the Blessed One — i.e., form as a clinging-aggregate... feeling... perception... fabrications... consciousness as a clinging-aggregate: If, with regard to these five clinging-aggregates, Ven. Khemaka assumes nothing to be self or belonging to self, then Ven. Khemaka is an arahant, devoid of fermentations.'\"", "entities": [[215, 226, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn22.089.than.html", "title": "Khemaka Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"Just as any seeds that exhibit growth, increase, & proliferation, all do so in dependence on the earth; or just as any activities requiring strength that are done, all are done in dependence on the earth; in the same way, Master Gotama, an individual with form as self, taking a stance on form, produces merit or demerit. An individual with feeling as self... with perception as self... with fabrications as self... with consciousness as self, taking a stance on consciousness, produces merit or demerit.\"", "entities": [[230, 236, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.035.than.html", "title": "Cula-Saccaka Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"What do you think, Anuradha: Do you regard the Tathagata as being in form?... Elsewhere than form?... In feeling?... Elsewhere than feeling?... In perception?... Elsewhere than perception?... In fabrications?... Elsewhere than fabrications?... In consciousness?... Elsewhere than consciousness?\"", "entities": [[48, 57, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn22.086.than.html", "title": "Anuradha Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "A second time, the Blessed One said to Saccaka the Nigaṇṭha-son: \"What do you think, Aggivessana? When you say, 'Form is my self,' do you wield power over that form: 'May my form be thus, may my form not be thus'?\"", "entities": [[19, 30, "PERSON"], [39, 63, "PERSON"], [85, 96, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.035.than.html", "title": "Cula-Saccaka Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "[The Blessed One said:] \"There are these four qualities, TigerPaw, that lead to a lay person's happiness and well-being in this life. Which four? Being consummate in initiative, being consummate in vigilance, admirable friendship, and maintaining one's livelihood in tune.", "entities": [[5, 16, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an08.054.than.html", "title": "Dighajanu (Vyagghapajja) Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "Then the thought occurred to Alavika the nun: \"Now who has recited this verse — a human being or a non-human one?\" Then it occurred to her: \"This is Mara the Evil One, who has recited this verse wanting to arouse fear, horripilation, & terror in me, wanting to make me fall away from seclusion.\"", "entities": [[149, 153, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn05.001.than.html", "title": "Alavika Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"And through this line of reasoning one may know how the eye is not the fetter of forms, nor are forms the fetter of the eye, but whatever desire & passion arises in dependence on the two of them: That is the fetter there. The ear is not the fetter of sounds... The nose is not the fetter of aromas... The tongue is not the fetter of flavors... The body is not the fetter of tactile sensations... The intellect is not the fetter of ideas, nor are ideas the fetter of the intellect, but whatever desire & passion arises in dependence on the two of them: That is the fetter there. There is an eye in the Blessed One. The Blessed One sees forms with the eye. There is no desire or passion in the Blessed One. The Blessed One is well-released in mind.", "entities": [[602, 613, "PERSON"], [619, 630, "PERSON"], [693, 704, "PERSON"], [710, 721, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn35.191.than.html", "title": "Kotthita Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "On one occasion the Blessed One was staying near Rajagaha at the Squirrels' Sanctuary. Now at that time, when the king's assembly had gathered and was sitting together in the royal palace, this topic of conversation arose: \"Money [1] is allowable for the Sakyan-son contemplatives. The Sakyan-son contemplatives consent to money. The Sakyan-son contemplatives accept money.\"", "entities": [[20, 31, "PERSON"], [49, 57, "GPE"], [65, 85, "LOC"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "SN", "identifier": "sn42.010.than.html", "title": "Maniculaka Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"Given that I have declared, Ananda, that bodily misconduct, verbal misconduct, & mental misconduct should not be done, these are the drawbacks one can expect when doing what should not be done: One can fault oneself; observant people, on close examination, criticize one; one's bad reputation gets spread about; one dies confused; and — on the break-up of the body, after death — one reappears in the plane of deprivation, the bad destination, the lower realms, in hell. Given that I have declared, Ananda, that bodily misconduct, verbal misconduct, & mental misconduct should not be done, these are the drawbacks one can expect when doing what should not be done.", "entities": [[29, 35, "PERSON"], [500, 506, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an02.018.than.html", "title": "Ekamsena Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"Thus this is a cause, this is a reason, this is an origination, this is a requisite condition for seeking, i.e., craving. Thus, Ananda, these two phenomena [the chain of conditions leading from craving to birth, aging, and death, and the chain of conditions leading from craving to quarrels, etc.], as a duality, flow back into one place at feeling.", "entities": [[129, 135, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "DN", "identifier": "dn.15.0.than.html", "title": "Maha-nidana Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"Very well, then: 'The cosmos is finite... The cosmos is infinite... The soul & the body are the same... The soul is one thing and the body another... After death a Tathagata exists... After death a Tathagata does not exist... After death a Tathagata both does & does not exist... After death a Tathagata neither does nor does not exist. Only this is true; anything otherwise is worthless.' Is this the sort of view you have?\"", "entities": [[165, 174, "PERSON"], [199, 208, "PERSON"], [241, 250, "PERSON"], [295, 304, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an10.096.than.html", "title": "Kokanuda Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"No matter what Gotama the contemplative says, Mallika endorses it: 'If that was said by the Blessed One, great king, then that's the way it is.' Just as, no matter what his teacher says, a pupil endorses it: 'That's the way it is, teacher. That's the way it is.' In the same way, no matter what Gotama the contemplative says, Mallika endorses it: 'If that was said by the Blessed One, great king, then that's the way it is.' Go away, Mallika! Out of my sight!\"", "entities": [[16, 22, "PERSON"], [93, 104, "PERSON"], [296, 302, "PERSON"], [373, 384, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.087.than.html", "title": "Piyajatika Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"Yes, lord,\" Ven. Sona answered the Blessed One. Then, having given this exhortation to Ven. Sona, the Blessed One — as a strong man might stretch out his bent arm or bend his outstretched arm — disappeared from the Cool Wood and appeared on Vulture Peak Mountain.", "entities": [[36, 47, "PERSON"], [103, 114, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an06.055.than.html", "title": "Sona Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "Then Ven. Ananda approached the nun and, on arrival, sat down on a prepared seat. As he was sitting there, he said to the nun: \"This body, sister, comes into being through food. And yet it is by relying on food that food is to be abandoned.", "entities": [[10, 16, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an04.159.than.html", "title": "Bhikkhuni Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"No, lord. King Seniya Bimbisara of Magadha hasn't provoked me, nor have the Licchavis of Vesali, nor has some other hostile king. There is a bandit in my realm, lord, named Angulimala: brutal, bloody-handed, devoted to killing & slaying, showing no mercy to living beings. He has turned villages into non-villages, towns into non-towns, settled countryside into unsettled countryside. Having repeatedly killed human beings, he wears a garland made of fingers. I am going to stamp him out.\" [1]", "entities": [[11, 32, "PERSON"], [36, 43, "GPE"], [77, 86, "NORP"], [90, 96, "GPE"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.086.than.html", "title": "Angulimala Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "Then the brahman Nalijangha, delighting in & approving of the Blessed One's words, got up from his seat and went to Queen Mallika. On arrival, he told her all that had been said in his conversation with the Blessed One.", "entities": [[62, 73, "PERSON"], [116, 129, "PERSON"], [207, 218, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.087.than.html", "title": "Piyajatika Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "\"Being sustained, Ananda, he is sustained by the supreme sustenance; for this — the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception — is the supreme sustenance. There is [however] the case where a monk, having practiced in this way — 'It should not be, it should not occur to me; it will not be, it will not occur to me. What is, what has come to be, that I abandon' — obtains equanimity. He does not relish that equanimity, does not welcome it, does not remain fastened to it. As he does not relish that equanimity, does not welcome it, does not remain fastened to it, his consciousness is not dependent on it, is not sustained by it (does not cling to it). Without clinging/sustenance, Ananda, a monk is totally unbound.\"", "entities": [[18, 24, "PERSON"], [691, 697, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "MN", "identifier": "mn.106.than.html", "title": "Aneñja-sappaya Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
{"text": "The Blessed One said: \"Now what, monks, is five-factored noble right concentration? There is the case where a monk — quite withdrawn from sensuality, withdrawn from unskillful qualities — enters and remains in the first jhana: rapture and pleasure born from withdrawal, accompanied by directed thought and evaluation. He permeates and pervades, suffuses and fills this very body with the rapture and pleasure born from withdrawal. There is nothing of his entire body unpervaded by rapture and pleasure born from withdrawal.", "entities": [[4, 15, "PERSON"]], "meta": {"nikaya": "AN", "identifier": "an05.028.than.html", "title": "Samadhanga Sutta", "para_seq": null}}
